Inventory of the Klaus Kirchner collection
Hoover Institution Archives
- Soviet Central Series, 1941-1945; 1-5 (Box 1-5:)
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 213, 1942 July (Folder 3: 1731)
    17x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 213 ... Enormous German losses near Voronezh... Attack of the Russian air force on Königsberg...]. Photograph: German POWs in the reading room of their camp.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 209, 1942 July (Folder 3: 1733)
    17x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 209... Increase of weapons production in England... Finland cannot continue the war...]. Photograph: [Continually American weapons arrive in Russia... Unloading of American tanks in a Russian port]
  - AN DAS DEUTSCHE VOLK! Landsleute! Männer und Frauen! In ernster..., 1942 July (Folder 3: 1738)
    15x22 cm - 4 - preservation: 1. Description: [To the German people! Countrymen! Men and women! In this dangerous hour, we German officers and soldiers in the Soviet-Union turn to you... No peace with Hitler...]. Two pages of facsimile signatures of POWs.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 210, 1942 July (Folder 3: 1739)
    17x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper; [News from Foreign Countries No. 210 Arrival of American troops in Northern Ireland. The English fleet is ready to land troops on the continent...] Photograph: [New American troops are arriving in Northern Ireland.]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 185, 1942 July (Folder 3: 1742)
    16x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: Erroneously the code printed on the leaflet is 4712 [Anti-war leaflets in German cities... What is happening in Germany?... No. 185... You do have to come back.. We may die from hunger]. Drawing: [Bread! Bread!]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 214, 1942 July (Folder 3: 1745)
    17x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 214... Destruction of the German divisions near Voronezh... Russian bombers over Königsberg... Success of the Soviet air force ... German soldiers refuse to fight...] Photograph: [German POWs in Russian captivity. After the war they will return to their loved ones]
  - Wie die Kriegsgefangenen in Sowjetrussland leben Nr. 53, 1942 July (Folder 3: 1747)
    16x21 ern - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [How the POWs are living in Soviet Russia No. 53... We do not doubt Russians take good care of POWs... I got well again in captivity... They told us lies about the Red Army...]. Photograph: German POWs receive food.
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 215, 1942 August (Folder 3: 1763)
    17x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 215... Germany is in the West not protected... Enormous losses at the Eastern front... In one week 503 German aircraft destroyed...]. Photomontage: [You will be the next one!]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 186, 1942 August (Folder 3: 1765)
    16x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [What is happening in Germany? No. 186... Königsberg in flames... Not much left in Rostock… Cologne destroyed... Message of the commander of the British air force to the German people...]. Air Marshal of the RAF is addressing the Germans, see also British leaflet G. 41/1942. Photograph: A marching column of German POWs. [Only captivity guarantees, you will stay alive and will return safely]
  - Wie die Kriegsgefangenen in Sowjetrussland leben Nr. 54, 1942 August (Folder 3: 1767)
    16x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [How the POWs are living in Soviet Russia No. 54... We believe Stalin's order No. 55... Here everything is different and better than we had expected... Listen to our radio broadcasts in the German language...]. Photograph: German POWs in a Russian hospital.
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 216, 1942 August (Folder 3: 1780)
    21x17 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 216... Hitler is thinning out Germany... losses of the Germans in the Southern part of Russia. .. Without fear into Russian captivity...] Photograph: [These are those who survived from a German mechanized regiment. Now they march to a POW camp]
  - Wie die Kriegsgefangenen in Sowjetrussland leben Nr. 55, 1942 August (Folder 3: 1781)
    16x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [How the POWs are living in Soviet Russia No. 55... How a group of 60 soldiers surrendered ...Greetings to relatives and friends in Dessau...]. Photograph: German POWs are resting after working in a field.
  - 10 GEBOTE DIE JEDER DEUTSCHE Soldat..., 1942 August (Folder 3: 1782)
    10x21 cm - 4 - paper: blue - preservation: 1. Description: [10 commandments which every soldier has to know. Remember! The order of the Council of the Peoples Commissars of the USSR guarantees all POWs their life, good treatment, information of relatives and the return home after the war... It is always helpful to have a Russian leaflet. If you don't have one just raise your hands and speak loud and clear "RUSS, SDAIUS!"] 6 drawings by Erich Weinert.
  - Papi ist tot. Klag Hitler an! Der hat es getan! Zögere keinen Augenblick!..., 1942 August (Folder 3: 1790)
    22x15 cm - 2 - paper: blue - preservation: 1. Description: [Daddy is dead. Accuse Hitler! He did it! Do not hesitate a minute! Tomorrow it will be too late!]. Photomontage.
  - Nie wird Vater wiederkommen: Hitler hat ihn uns genommen! Soldat, vergiss das nicht!..., 1942 July (Folder 3: 1791)
    15x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Daddy will never come back. Hitler has taken him from us! Soldier, do not forget that! Offensive means: DEATH...]. Photomontage, see leaflet code 1722.
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 188, 1942 August (Folder 3: 1792)
    16x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [What is happening in Germany? No. 188... Letter to sergeant... The despair of a German mother...]. Photomontage: [The soldiers fall. The stocks are rising]
  - Wie die Kriegsgefangenen in Sowjetrussland leben Nr. 56, 1942 August (Folder 3: 1793)
    16x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [How the POWs are living in Soviet Russia No. 56... Three German fighter pilots desert to the Russians... Their aircraft had enough gasoline and was in good order... Declaration of the German pilots... A letter of a German soldier has reached his relatives...] Photograph: [German POWs in Russian captivity are playing chess...]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 218, 1942 August (Folder 3: 1798)
    16x21 cm - 2 - paper: red - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 218... Mighty offensive of the Red Army... Heavy losses of the Germans at the river Don...]
  - 12. August 1942. An die Kameraden der 161. Inf. Division, der 14..., 1942 August (Folder 3: 1799)
    17x25 cm - 4 - preservation: 1. Description: The leaflet is handwritten it contains a three-page-list of facsimile signatures of German POWs. [Dear Comrades! I am sure you are thinking about us, who had been taken prisoner... We have been treated well· especially by the Commissars...]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 189, 1942 August (Folder 3: 1800)
    16x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [What is happening in Germany? No. 189... What have the AEG worker and what have the employers won by this war?... The best goods are for the Plutocrats...] Caricature: [Goering: yes, war is hard business]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 214, 1942 August (Folder 3: 1801)
    17x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 214... Declaration of the commander of the American troops in Europe... Successful fights of the Yugoslav partisan army... People's revenge take the lives of Hitler's and Gestapo men... After the murder of Heydrich the chief of the Gestapo in Agram was killed... French partisans are fighting Hitler fascists in Paris...]
  - SONDERMELDUNG EINE BEGEGNUNG VON WELTHISTORISCHER..., 1942 August (Folder 3: 1802)
    17x24 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Special announcement. A meeting of world historic importance. The three biggest world powers agreed on the strategic and complete destruction of Hitler...Telegram of Churchill to Stalin...]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 215, 1942 August (Folder 3: 1823)
    17x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 215... Russia, England and the USA reached an agreement on the strategic offensive against Germany... 50000 armed French partisans are ready to fight Hitler...]. Photograph: [English 16-ton-tanks, type Valentine. They are the equipment of one of the many English tank divisions]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 220, 1942 August (Folder 3: 1825)
    17x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 220... The Soviet air force attacked Danzig, Königsberg and Tilsit] Photograph: [On the Eastern front: German soldiers surrender and save their lives.]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 221, 1942 August (Folder 3: 1826)
    17x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 221... A complete German company is surrendering... Soldiers find ways and means to get away] Three portrait photographs of German pilots having flown into Russian captivity.]
  - Der Dank des Führers..., 1942 August (Folder 3: 1830)
    14x16 cm - 4 - preservation: 1. Description: [German soldiers! Read, about the fate of a soldier's family...]. The soldier's mother informs him how his wife was not able to work on the farm alone and tried to commit suicide. Her life is saved but she is turned over to an insane asylum and was sterilized there. Facsimile of letters describing the drama and sterilization of the wife of a German soldier.
  - Die Wahrheit über die Fliegerangriffe auf deutsche Städte DEUTSCHE SOLDATEN!..., 1942 August (Folder 3: 1833)
    14x16 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [The truth about air raids on German cities... The Soviet air force attacked cities and industrial centers in East Prussia, Upper Silesia and Poland... The Soviet air force lost not one single airplane...]. Drawing: Hitler and Goebbels attack Soviet airplanes with printers ink.
  - 10 FRAGEN UND ANTWORTEN Warum werfen wir gleichzeitig Bomben und Flugblätter ab?, 1942 August (Folder 3: 1834)
    14x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [10 Questions and answers 1. Why do we disseminate bombs and leaflets at the same time? Because we want to destroy your armament industry and because we want to tell you the truth about the war...]. Note: Dissemination of leaflets are rarely mentioned on leaflets themselves.
  - SONDERMELDUNG des... Die Sowjettruppen im Vormarsch..., 1942 August (Folder 3: 1837)
    14x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Special announcement of the Bureau of Information of the Soviet-Union. Soviet troops are advancing... In the region of Kalinin...]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 222, 1942 August (Folder 3: 1847)
    17x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 222. Offensive of the Red Army on the Middle and Kalinin front... German officers are leaving Hitler's army... 542 German airplanes had been destroyed... A German pilot deserted by flying over to the Red Army...] Photograph: [German POWs captured during recent fighting]
  - Was lehrt die Landungsaktion von Dieppe?, 1942 August (Folder 3: 1848)
  - DEUTSCHE SOLDATEN! LASST EUCH RATEN: RUFT DEN RUSSEN..., 1942 August (Folder 3: 1850)
    23x16 cm - 2 - paper: red - preservation: 1. Description: [German soldiers! Take our advice: Call out to the Russians: "SDAIUS TOVARISCH, NE STRELAITE"...] Photomontage and poem by Erich Weinert: [Do not wait longer]
  - Wie die Kriegsgefangenen in Sowjetrussland leben Nr. 60, 1942 September (Folder 3: 1853)
    14x21 cm - 4 - preservation: 2, edge damaged. Description of leaflet newspaper: [How the POWs are living in Soviet Russia No. 60... He is looking at the picture of his beloved child. He knows: as soon as the war is over...]. 9 photographs: German POWs are well cared for in Russian captivity.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 216, 1942 September (Folder 3: 1855)
    17x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 216... Brazil declared war on Germany... 50,000 armed French partisans are ready to fight Hitler...] Photograph: [English 16-ton-tanks, type Valentine. They are the armament of one of the many English tank divisions.]
  - Es langt nicht mehr - nicht hin, nicht her! Deutsche Männer und Frauen!..., 1942 September (Folder 3: 1856)
    11x15 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [It's not enough by far! German men and women! At the price of hundred thousands of German soldiers Hitler succeeded to advance in the Southern part of the Eastern front ... Write your relatives at the front to surrender...]. Dissemination was intended inside Germany, see addressee [German men and women!...]. The leaflet was printed without a safe conduct.
  - AUSLÄNDER NEHMEN DEINEN PLATZ EIN!, 1942 September (Folder 3: 1857)
    14x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of pornographic leaflet: [Foreigners take your place... Some of them have all possible types of venereal disease... It could happen to you coming home and being met by a black haired bastard. You would have the pleasure to raise this child...]. Two drawings by Erich Weinert: [While you sit in a bunker your wife is having fun with a foreigner.]. See also leaflet code 1910.
  - An die deutschen Rüstungsarbeiter im Waffenrock!, 1942 September (Folder 3: 1858)
    14x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [To the German workers in armament factories in uniform!... In the face of death think about this... The war is for the rich. The soldiers provide the corpses.]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 191, 1942 September (Folder 3: 1870)
    17x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [What is happening in Germany? No. 191... The German people want peace... Acts of sabotage in Germany... Mass executions in Berlin. Anti-war demonstrations in a cinema in Berlin ] Drawing: [Down with Hitler! Down with the war...]
  - Wann ist der Krieg zu Ende?..., 1942 September (Folder 3: 1876)
    11x15 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [When will the war end?...]. Dissemination was intended inside Germany, see addressee [German men and women!...], without a safe conduct.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 217, 1942 September (Folder 3: 1892)
    16x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 217 Greece Yugoslavia... France Belgium Norway...]. Map: [Yugoslavia in August 1942...]
  - Du denkst, wenn du gefangen bist, Dann..., 1942 September (Folder 3: 1899)
    11x15 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [You think if you are in captivity, you cannot write to your mother...] Poem by Erich Weinert. Two-language safe conduct on reverse.
  - WIE SIE WIRKLICH DENKEN (Aus dem Tagebuch des Obersten Schilling..., 1942 September (Folder 3: 1902)
    14x21 cm - 4 - preservation: 1. Description: [How they really think. From the diary of Colonel Schilling...]. Excerpts and facsimile of a diary. This is a forgery by the Soviet propagandists, i.e. a "black" propaganda leaflet.
  - DEUTSCHLAND OHNE DEUTSCHE Deutsche Soldaten! Während Ihr..., 1942 September (Folder 3: 1910)
    13x18 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of pornographic leaflet: [Germany without Germans. German soldiers! While you are perishing in far away countries the German cities and villages are populated by foreigners... Foreigners take your place in the work shop, in the fields. Foreigners are sleeping with your women and make them children, infect them with venereal disease. The luck of your family is gone...]. Two drawings by Erich Weinert: [While you sit in a bunker your wife is having fun with a foreigner.] See also leaflet code 1857, different text.
  - 73 deutsche Divisionen im Sommer 1942 an der Ostfrontvernichtet..., 1942 September (Folder 3: 1911)
    14x17 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [73 German divisions destroyed in summer 1942 at the Eastern front ... You will not escape a new winter in Russia! You will not escape your decline...]
  - Wen die Kugel verschont, den packt der weisse Tod. Deutsche Soldaten!, 1942 September (Folder 3: 1931)
    16x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Those who are being spared by the bullet will be caught by death ... Think about the Russian winter in 19411... The retreat in 1942 will bring you a catastrophe...] Two photomontages: soldiers dying in the snow.
  - Wer ist Hitler? Frontsoldat! Du weisst nicht, was heute in der Heimat..., 1942 September (Folder 3: 1932)
    14x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Who is Hitler... You don't know what is known at home... Germany will rise, down with Hitler!...]
  - Wie die Kriegsgefangenen in Sowjetrussland leben Nr. 61, 1942 October (Folder 3: 1950)
    14x18 cm - 4 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [How the POWs are living in Soviet Russia No. 61... German soldiers! Your officers and the Goebbels propaganda feed you with impertinent lies about Russian captivity. Read and see how your comrades are being treated in Russian captivity...]. Six photographs: German POWs in Russian captivity.
  - EINE NEUE HITLERLÜGE Soldaten! Hitler lügt, wenn er in seiner Rede..., 1942 October (Folder 3: 1953)
    14x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [A new lie of Hitler. Soldiers! Hitler is lying... when he tells the soldier: "You can be assured. Behind you is your home town which will never let you down." What an impertinent cynical lie...]
  - FÜR RADIOSTATIONEN UND - LAUTSPRECHERANLAGEN... Was treibt die SS?..., 1942 October (Folder 3: 1962)
    12x23 cm - 4 - preservation: 1. Description: [For radio stations and loudspeaker installations... What is the SS up to?... Poem by Erich Weinert. What does Hitler need the SS for?... Letters from Germany about the SS… News from foreign countries...]. Note: This is not a leaflet! The text was used for vocal communication only. The Soviet Government used, together with its leaflets, radio broadcasts and also sent messages by loudspeaker trying to influence German soldiers.
  - Wie sorgt Hitler für die Kriegsinvaliden?..., 1942 October (Folder 3: 1971)
    13x18 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [How Hitler is caring for the war invalids... In Germany only 45 of 100 wounded soldiers can continue to serve in the Wehrmacht. The others die or remain cripples... Hitler does not care about the war cripples...]. Drawing: the cripple is not allowed in a restaurant.
  - Eine ernste Warnung. DEUTSCHE..., 1942 October (Folder 3: 1977)
    10x16 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [An important warning. On 4th October, 1942 Goering declared: "The loss of the war means annihilation for the German people. The Nazi big wigs feel their unavoidable decline coming. They intend to tie their own fate to that of the German people...]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 218, 1942 October (Folder 3: 1978)
    17x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 218... In front of Stalingrad hundred thousands of Germans have died... General Guderian died at the Eastern front... German soldiers and officers deserted from Hitler's army... Massive unrest in France...]. Photograph: [Mass production of airplanes in the USA.].
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 193, 1942 October (Folder 3: 1989)
    16x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: - [What is happening in Germany? No. 193... Lübeck was turned to a heap of rubble... What the soldier on furlough can expect at home... Wiesbaden, Mainz and Schierstein in flames...]. Drawing.
  - Ihr kamt zwar nach Russland hinein..., 1942 October (Folder 3: 2001)
    21x13 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [It was possible for you to enter Russia but you will not leave it alive!... Many wanted to conquer Russia but all these undertakings ended with the destruction of their armies... The lesson of history is: Russia cannot be defeated...]. Five drawings by Erich Weinert, caption: [Winter is coming, 50 degrees, Your DEATH, SOLDIER!]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 223, 1942 November (Folder 3: 2016)
    16x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 223 ... Stalingrad frustrated Hitler's plan for this summer... The battle for Stalingrad is the turning point of the whole war...]. Caricature: [Hitler is getting nervous about Stalingrad...]
  - ROMMELS ARMEE AUFS HAUPT GESCHLAGEN. Die nordafrikanische Küste von..., 1942 November (Folder 3: 2047)
    13x16 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Rommel's army hit on the head. The North African coast occupied by English and American troops…the complete Mediterranean sea in the hands of England and America...]. Map of North Africa.
  - WAS HAT STALIN GESAGT? Die Ziele der Sowjetunion im Kriege gegen Hitler..., 1942 November (Folder 4: 2082)
    17x13 cm - paper: blue, paper: green - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: Excerpts from Stalin's speech on the 25th year of the Bolshevik revolution. [The aims of the Soviet-Union in the war against Hitler...]
  - WAS HAT STALIN GESAGT? Zwei Koalitionen - zwei Programme..., 1942 November (Folder 4: 2083)
    17x13 cm - paper: red, paper: rose - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: Excerpts from Stalin's speech on the 25th year of the Bolshevik revolution. [Two coalitions - two programs...]
  - WAS HAT STALIN GESAGT? Zusammenbruch des strategischen..., 1942 November (Folder 4: 2084)
    17x13 cm - paper: blue, paper: rose - 2 - preservation: 1- 11.1942 - description: Excerpts from Stalin's speech on the 25th year of the Bolshevik revolution. [Breakdown of Hitler's strategic plan...]
  - DEUTSCHE MATROSEN! Eure unfähige Leitung hat sich bitter verrechnet..., 1942 November (Folder 4: 2088)
    12x18cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [German sailors! Your incompetent leadership made a severe mistake. They told you the USA would never be able to transport its troops across the ocean...]. Note: Leaflets addressed directly to sea or air men are rarely seen, it is difficult to reach them.
  - Der englisch-amerikanische Vormarsch in Afrika ist das Vorspiel zur..., 1942 November (Folder 4: 2096)
    12x15cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [The English-American advance in Africa is the overture for the Second Front. What happened in Africa...]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 195, 1942 November (Folder 4: 2097)
    17x21 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description: [What is happening in Germany? No. 195... The SS is ruling in Germany… The SS is Hitler's weapon against the German Army..]. Poem and caricature: [What is an SS-man?...]
  - Der Sturz des Hitlerstaates ist Eure Rettung..., 1942 November (Folder 4: 2098)
    13x18 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description: [The deposal of Hitler's state will save you... What did Hitler's state bring you?...]
  - ERFOLGREICHE OFFENSIVE DER SOWJETTRUPPEN IM RAUM VON Stalingrad..., 1942 November (Folder 4: 2100)
    11x14 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description: [Successful offensive of the Soviet troops in the area of Stalingrad?... In three days of fighting 12,000 prisoners had been brought in... The offensive will be continued...]
  - Rettet Euch, ehe es zu spät ist!... Im Raum von Stalingrad ist die Rote Armee zur... SOLDATEN DES MITTELABSCHNITTS..., 1942 November (Folder 4: 2108)
    14x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [Save yourselves before it is too late!... In the area of Stalingrad the Red Army has started its offensive... To the soldiers of the middle part of the Eastern front...]